Guide to the National Education Association-Councils records, 1849-1983 NEA1004.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association Records-Councils
1849-1983
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association of the United States
NEA1004.RG
18.5 Linear Feet
Biographical/Historical note
The National Education Association (NEA) is the largest professional organization and largest labor union in the United States, representing public school teachers and other support personnel, faculty and staffers at colleges and universities, retired educators, and college students preparing to become teachers. In 2010, the NEA had 3.2 million members and is located in Washington, D.C. The group holds a congressional charter under Title 36 of the United States Code granted in 1906.
The NEA describes itself as a professional employee organization. The mission of the National Education Association is "to advocate for education professionals and to unite our members and the nation to fulfill the promise of public education to prepare every student to succeed in a diverse and interdependent world."
The NEA is a volunteer-based organization that relies upon its members to perform much of the Association's work. The members are supported by staff at the local, state, and national levels with the stated goal of "building great public schools for every student."
In 1857, Thomas W. Valentine, president of the New York State Teachers Association, issued a nation-wide invitation to teachers to unite in Philadelphia behind a common voice for America's growing public school system. After the meeting, the National Teachers Association (NTA) was formed with a membership of about 100. Minority educators were allowed to join at the start, but women were not allowed to join until 1866.
In 1870, the NTA merged with the American Normal School Association, the National Association of School Superintendents, and the Central College Association renaming itself the National Education Association. For the first 100 years of its existence, the NEA was controlled by administrators, and worked to further the interests of the "education profession" as a whole.
In the 1960's, after the first passage of a collective bargaining law for public employees, the NEA adopted union activities in addition to its operations as a professional association.
The NEA merged with the American Teachers Association (ATA), formerly the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools (NATCS) in 1966.
In 1998, a proposed merger with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) failed when it was rejected by NEA's Representative Assembly. Several NEA state affiliates have merged with their AFT counterparts, effectively forming a single association.
Over the years, the NEA has been a leader in national education reform and improvement movements. It has worked to improve the education provided to American school children through lobbying and campaigning on the local and national level as well as by promoting strong teacher education programs and continuous professional assessment and development.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the councils of the NEA. The collection contains six series reflecting the offices that created or held these records. The six series are: Council for Research in Education, Council of National Organizations on Children and Youth, Higher Education Council, National Council of Education, Council on Instruction, and National Council on Teacher Retirement.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into roughly alphabetical series based upon the NEA's organization. Records have been allocated largely to their offices of origin and reflect the work done within the offices, departments, divisions and units. Due to the immense size of the collection and the constraints placed upon the finding aid by the archival management system utilized by George Washington University, the collection was further divided up into parts.
Organized into 6 series: Council for Research in Education; Council of National Organizations on Children and Youth; Higher Education Council; National Council on Education; Council on Instruction; and National Council on Teacher Retirement.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. These files are restricted. Those files flagged as restricted are subject to review by Special Collections staff before being made available for research. As researchers request materials, a review of the documents will take place. Staff will remove any documents with social security numbers, employee numbers or other sensitive identifying information. Any document found including this information is closed for 90 years from date of creation, or until verifiable proof of a person's death is given. After these documents are removed the folder will be available for research. In some cases, items may be photocopied and redacted. The redacted copy will then be placed in the publicly available folder. All other materials in a folder will be freely available for immediate use and will be marked as having been reviewed by Special Collections staff. After folders have been reviewed using these procedures and the confidential materials have been removed, the restriction shall be lifted.
Labor unions; Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Teachers; Education -- United States -- History; Professional Employees; Professional Associations; Education--Research; Teachers' assistants
- Council for Research in Education, 1957-1964; Series 1; 3 Linear Feet
  Biographical/Historical note
  In 1957, Percival M. Symonds urged that organizations with a basic interest in educational research should establish a national council. In 1958, the representatives of 20 organizations agreed that they would pursue this plan and in 1959, steps were established to create a council.
  In 1960, the first meeting was held adopting a constitution, bylaws, electing officers, and filing papers for incorporation with the District of Columbia as the Council for Research in Education.
  The Council's purpose was to "provide the means whereby the wide interdisciplinary interests and capabilities in the scientific approach to educational research may coordinate their strengths in seeking solutions to major educational problems".
  The Council was soon dissolved in 1963.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by title, and chronologically within the same title.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains materials created by the Council for Research in Education. The files include correspondence with member groups, reports, Board of Directors and Delegates meeting papers, and meeting minutes.
  - Application, circa 1962; Series 1 (Box 1510, Folder 1)
  - "A Background Paper for the Council for Research in Education", circa 1962; Series 1 (Box 1510, Folder 2)
  - Board of Delegates-General, 1960-1962; Series 1 (Box 1510, Folder 3)
  - Board of Delegates-Meeting, January 1961; Series 1 (Box 1510, Folder 4)
  - Board of Delegates-Meeting [file 1/2], January 1962; Series 1 (Box 1510, Folder 5)
  - Board of Delegates-Meeting [file 2/2], January 1962; Series 1 (Box 1510, Folder 6)
  - Board of Delegates-Meeting [file 1/2], January 1963; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 1)
  - Board of Delegates-Meeting [file 2/2], January 1963; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, January 1960; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, October 1960; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, January 1961; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 5)
    Contains 1 photo and 1 negative.
  - Board of Directors Meeting, October 1961; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, January 1962; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, April 1962; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, October 1962; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, January 1963; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, October 1963; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 11)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, February 1960; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 12)
  - Constitution, March 1960; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 13)
  - Constitution-Early Drafts, 1958-1960; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence/Reports, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1511, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence/Reports [file 1/2], 1960; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence/Reports [file 2/2], 1960; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence/Reports, 1961; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence/Reports, 1962; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence/Reports, 1963; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 5)
  - Dissolution, 1963; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 6)
  - English for the Academically Talented Student, 1960, 1969; Series 1 (Box 4593, Folder 3)
  - Expense Forms, circa 1963; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 7)
  - Expense Vouchers, 1961-1963; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 8)
  - Finance Committee, 1961-1962; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 9)
  - Financial Report by the Treasurer, 1960-1963; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 10)
  - Financial Statement, 1959-1963; Series 1 (Box 1512, Folder 11)
  - Form Letters Sent to Delegates and to Officers, 1960-1962; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 1)
  - Foundations, 1960; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 2)
  - Information Leaflet, 1960-1962; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 3)
  - Interim Committee Report, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 4)
  - Legal Services, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 5)
  - Letterhead, 1960-1963; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 6)
    Contains 4 photos.
  - Materials Leading to the Formation of Council, 1957-1959; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 7)
  - Member Groups-Adult Education Association of the USA, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 8)
  - Member Groups-American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation, 1959-1963; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 9)
  - Member Groups-American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 10)
  - Member Groups-American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 11)
  - Member Groups-American Association of School Administrators, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 12)
  - Member Groups-American College Personnel Association, 1961; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 13)
  - Member Groups-American Educational Research Association, 1963; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 14)
  - Member Groups-American Psychological Association, 1960-1963; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 15)
  - Member Groups-American Statistical Association, 1960-1962; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 16)
  - Member Groups-American Vocational Association, 1959-1963; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 17)
  - Member Groups-Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, 1959-1961; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 18)
  - Member Groups-Association of College Admissions Counselors, 1960-1961; Series 1 (Box 1513, Folder 19)
  - Member Groups-Council for Exceptional Children, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 1)
  - Member Groups-Department of Elementary School Principals, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 2)
  - Member Groups-Educational Testing Service, 1961-1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 3)
  - Member Groups-List of, March 1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 4)
  - Member Groups-National Association for Research in Science Teaching, 1960-1963; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 5)
  - Member Groups-National Association of Secondary School Principals, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 6)
  - Member Groups-National Council for the Social Studies, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 7)
  - Member Groups-National Council of Teachers of English, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 8)
  - Member Groups-National Council on Measurement in Education, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 9)
  - Member Groups-NEA, 1959-1963; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 10)
  - Member Groups-National Science Teachers Association, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 11)
  - Member Groups-Phi Delta Kappa, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1958; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1960; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1961; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, 1962; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1963; Series 1 (Box 1514, Folder 18)
  - Organizations Invited or Interested in Membership, 1959-1964; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 1)
  - Pictures, 1960-1963; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 2)
  - The Reporter, November 1961; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 3)
  - Reports of the Research Activities and Interests of Member Groups, April 1963; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 4)
  - Requisitions, 1960-1963; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 5)
  - Science for the Academically Talented Student, 1959; Series 1 (Box 4593, Folder 4)
  - Seal for Council, 1961; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 6)
  - Tax Exemption Application, 1961; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 7)
  - University Council for Educational Administration, 1960-1961; Series 1 (Box 1515, Folder 8)
- Council of National Organizations on Children and Youth, 1929-1983; 1962-1978; Series 2; 8.25 Linear Feet
  Series contains materials created by the Council of National Organizations on Children and Youth. The files mainly include materials related to White House Conferences.
  Dwight D. Eisenhower's White House conference established the Council of National Organizations on Children and Youth, a national coordinating council serving some 400 individual youth and children's service providers, and state-based Committees for Children and Youth.
  The council was to implement the findings of the White House conference, to achieve greater coordination among the various programs and associations that sought to serve the needs of children and youth, to improve and speed the flow of useful information among interested organizations and agencies, to provide guidance in the planning of activities aimed toward improving children's services, and to identify new problems and issues as they arose in the provision of services to children.
  Separated Materials note
  This subseries contained numerous printed volumes which have been removed from the archival collection. They were:
  "The Nation's Children", volumes 1-3, 1960, Edited by Eli Ginzberg. "Congress and Federal Agencies, Directory for Child Advocates", 1977, by the CCY. "Slums and Suburbs", 1961, by James B. Conant. "Social Dynamite, the Report of the Conference on Unemployed, Out-of-School Youth in Urban Areas", 1961, by the NCCY. "Focus on Children and Youth", 1960, by the CNOCY. "Report to the Nation on Children and Youth", 1968, by the NCCY. "The States Report on Children and Youth", 1960, by the CNOCY. "Rural Youth in Crisis, Facts, Myths, and Social Change", 1963, by the NCCY.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  This collection is open for research. One folder, "Federal Quarterly Reports" contains social security numbers and other personal information that may be used to restrict access. Redacted copies of the materials may be provided upon interest by researchers.
  - 20th Anniversary Celebration of the 1963 March on Washington, 1983; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 1)
  - Accounting Figures-America's Children, circa 1979; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 2)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-Articles of Incorporation, 1972; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 3)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-Bylaws, circa 1972; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 4)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-DC Recorder of Deeds, 1973; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 5)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-Financial Arrangement with NCCY, 1972-1973; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 6)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-Financial Reports, 1972-1973; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 7)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-Invoices, July 1972-October 1972; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 8)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-Matching Grant, August 1972; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 9)
  - Action Now for Children and Youth-Outline, 1972; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 10)
  - Agendas (NCCY), 1961-1972; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 11)
  - Aims and Goals, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 12)
  - "America's Children: 1976", Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 13)
  - Annual Conference (Originals), 1979; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 9)
  - Annual Conference Materials, 1978; Series 2 (Box 1571, Folder 14)
  - Annual Conference Materials (CCY), November 1979; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meeting, June 1973; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meeting, 1974; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meeting (CNOCY), September 1974; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 4)
  - Annual Meeting, September 1975; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 5)
    Contains 5 photos.
  - Annual Meeting, December 1977; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 6)
  - Annual Meeting-Handouts, December 1977; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 7)
  - Annual Meeting-Miscellaneous Memoranda, October 1976; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report (Originals), 1979; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 10)
  - Articles of Amendment-Name Change to CCY, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1572, Folder 11)
  - Articles of Incorporation (NCOCY), 1973; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 1)
  - Associate Member Correspondence, 1978-1979; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 2)
  - Auditing History, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 3)
  - Audits, 1976-1978; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 4)
  - Banking Procedures, 1976-1978; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 5)
  - "Bicentennial Conference on Children, Conference Summary", February 1976; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 6)
  - Biennial-Executive Director Reports, 1964-1966; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 7)
  - Biennial-Meeting (CNOCY), April 1966; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 8)
  - Biennial-Meeting Agendas, 1962-1972; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 9)
  - Biennial-Meeting Minutes, 1964-1972; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 10)
  - Biennial-Officers and Member Election, 1966-1970; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 11)
  - Biennial-Program Committee, 1961-1964; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 12)
  - Bill LeStrange, Auditor, 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, April 1974; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 14)
  - Board Members (CCY), 1979; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 15)
  - Board Members of CCY (Originals), 1977-1979; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, 1979-1980; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 17)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, May 1975; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 18)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, July 1975; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 19)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, December 1975; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 20)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, October 1976; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 21)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, February 1977; Series 2 (Box 1573, Folder 22)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, October 1977; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, January 1978; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, June 1978; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, May 1980; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Meeting-Minutes, June 1973; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Meeting-Minutes, September 1973; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors Meeting-Minutes, January 1974; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors Meeting-Minutes, 1978; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Meeting-Minutes, April 1978; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 9)
  - Board-Staff Relations, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 10)
  - "Books for Leaders who Work with Children and Youth", 1963; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 11)
  - Budgets, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 12)
  - Budget (NCOCY), 1973-1977; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 13)
  - Budget Data, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 14)
  - Bylaws-Revised, January 1978; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 15)
  - Bylaws (NCCY), 1961-1963; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 16)
  - Bylaws (NCOCY), 1973-1978; Series 2 (Box 1574, Folder 17)
  - Calls to Meeting (NCCY), 1960-1972; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 1)
  - "A Child Advocate's Directory of Congressional and Federal Agencies and Offices", 1979-1980; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 2)
  - Child Health Assurance Program, 1978-1980; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 3)
  - "The Children's Political Checklist", November 1978; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 4)
  - Citizen's Conference on Priorities and Action for Children and Youth, 1971; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 5)
  - Closing and Transfer of Accounts, 1978; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 6)
  - Cluster Reports, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 7)
  - CNOCY-Executive Committee-Agendas, 1961-1972; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 8)
  - CNOCY-Executive Committee-Calls to Meeting, 1962-1972; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 9)
  - CNOCY-Executive Committee-Executive Director's Reports, 1962-1971; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 10)
  - CNOCY-Executive Committee-Financial Statements, 1961-1972; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 11)
  - CNOCY-Executive Committee-Lists, 1961-1973; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 12)
  - CNOCY-Executive Committee-Meeting Minutes, 1961-1972; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 13)
  - CNOCY-Executive Committee-Meeting, September 1970; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 14)
  - "Concern for Children", December 1970; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 15)
  - Contracts, 1974-1977; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence-Alexander, Chauncey, 1978-1979; Series 2 (Box 1575, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence-Moore, Emily, 1972; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-to Full Voting Members, 1978-1979; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 2)
  - Directory for Child Advocates, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 3)
  - DC Compensation Board, 1962-1967; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 4)
  - DC Compensation Board-Correspondence, 1966-1967; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 5)
  - DC Department of Licences and Inspection, 1958-1959; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 6)
  - Department of Social Welfare (NY), 1968-1972; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 7)
  - Developmental Grant Committee, 1972; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 8)
  - Director's Reports (NCCY), 1960-1972; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 9)
  - Draft Minutes of Appointment of Peg Jones, 1977; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 10)
  - Early Bird Conference, October 1978; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 11)
  - Early, Cassidy, and Chilling, 1974-1978; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, June 1973; Series 2 (Box 1576, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, October 1973; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, February 1974; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, March 1974; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, January 1975; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, February 1975; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, April 1975; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, October 1975; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, April 1976; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, May 1980; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, January 1978-June 1978; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 10)
  - Expenses to Dissolve the Coalition, 1980; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 11)
  - Federal Exemption from Income Tax, 1974; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 12)
  - Federal Quarterly Reports, 1967-1973; Series 2 (Box 1577, Folder 13)